===========================================================================
				   HVCS
	IBM "Hypervisor Virtual Console Server" Installation Guide
			  for Linux Kernel 2.6.4+
		    Copyright (C) 2004 IBM Corporation

===========================================================================
NOTE:Eight space tabs are the optimum editor setting for reading this file.
===========================================================================

	       Author(s) :  Ryan S. Arnold <rsa@us.ibm.com>
		       Date Created: March, 02, 2004
		       Last Changed: August, 24, 2004

---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Table of contents:

	1.  Driver Introduction:
	2.  System Requirements
	3.  Build Options:
		3.1  Built-in:
		3.2  Module:
	4.  Installation:
	5.  Connection:
	6.  Disconnection:
	7.  Configuration:
	8.  Questions & Answers:
	9.  Reporting Bugs:

---------------------------------------------------------------------------
1. Driver Introduction:

This is the device driver for the IBM Hypervisor Virtual Console Server,
"hvcs".  The IBM hvcs provides a tty driver interface to allow Linux user
space applications access to the system consoles of logically partitioned
operating systems (Linux and AIX) running on the same partitioned Power5
ppc64 system.  Physical hardware consoles per partition are not practical
on this hardware so system consoles are accessed by this driver using
firmware interfaces to virtual terminal devices.

---------------------------------------------------------------------------
2. System Requirements:

This device driver was written using 2.6.4 Linux kernel APIs and will only
build and run on kernels of this version or later.

This driver was written to operate solely on IBM Power5 ppc64 hardware
though some care was taken to abstract the architecture dependent firmware
calls from the driver code.

Sysfs must be mounted on the system so that the user can determine which
major and minor numbers are associated with each vty-server.  Directions
for sysfs mounting are outside the scope of this document.

---------------------------------------------------------------------------
3. Build Options:

The hvcs driver registers itself as a tty driver.  The tty layer
dynamically allocates a b