	   BusLogic MultiMaster and FlashPoint SCSI Driver for Linux

			 Version 2.0.15 for Linux 2.0
			 Version 2.1.15 for Linux 2.1

			      PRODUCTION RELEASE

				17 August 1998

			       Leonard N. Zubkoff
			       Dandelion Digital
			       lnz@dandelion.com

	 Copyright 1995-1998 by Leonard N. Zubkoff <lnz@dandelion.com>


				 INTRODUCTION

BusLogic, Inc. designed and manufactured a variety of high performance SCSI
host adapters which share a common programming interface across a diverse
collection of bus architectures by virtue of their MultiMaster ASIC technology.
BusLogic was acquired by Mylex Corporation in February 1996, but the products
supported by this driver originated under the BusLogic name and so that name is
retained in the source code and documentation.

This driver supports all present BusLogic MultiMaster Host Adapters, and should
support any future MultiMaster designs with little or no modification.  More
recently, BusLogic introduced the FlashPoint Host Adapters, which are less
costly and rely on the host CPU, rather than including an onboard processor.
Despite not having an onboard CPU, the FlashPoint Host Adapters perform very
well and have very low command latency.  BusLogic has recently provided me with
the FlashPoint Driver Developer's Kit, which comprises documentation and freely
redistributable source code for the FlashPoint SCCB Manager.  The SCCB Manager
is the library of code that runs on the host CPU and performs functions
analogous to the firmware on the MultiMaster Host Adapters.  Thanks to their
having provided the SCCB Manager, this driver now supports the FlashPoint Host
Adapters as well.

My primary goals in writing this completely new BusLogic driver for Linux are
to achieve the full performance that BusLogic SCSI Host Adapters and modern
SCSI peripherals are capable of, and to provide a highly robust driver that can
be depended upon for high performance mission critical applications.  All of
the major performance features can be configured from the Linux kernel command
line or at module initialization time, allowing individual installations to
tune driver performance and error recovery to their particular needs.

The latest information on Linux support for BusLogic SCSI Host Adapters, as
well as the most recent release of this driver and the latest firmware for the
BT-948/958/958D, will always be available from my Linux Home Page at URL
"http://sourceforge.net/projects/dandelion/".

Bug reports should be sent via electronic mail to "lnz@dandelion.com".  Please
include with the bug report the complete configuration messages reported by the
driver and SCSI subsystem at startup, along with any subsequent system messages
relevant to SCSI operations, and a detailed description of your system's
hardware configuration.

Mylex has been an excellent company to work with and I highly recommend their
products to the Linux community.  In November 1995, I was offered the
opportunity to become a beta test site for their latest MultiMaster product,
the BT-948 PCI Ultra SCSI Host Adapter, and then again for the BT-958 PCI Wide
Ultra SCSI Host Adapter in January 1996.  This was mutually beneficial since
Mylex received a degree and kind of testing that their own testing group cannot
readily achieve, and the Linux community has available high performance host
adapters that have been well tested with Linux even before being brought to
market.  This relationship has also given me the opportunity to interact
directly with their technical staff, to understand more about the internal
workings of their products, and in turn to educate them about the needs and
potential of the Linux community.

More recently, Mylex has reaffirmed the company's interest in supporting the
Linux community, and I am now working on a Linux driver for the DAC960 PCI RAID
Controllers.  Mylex's interest and support is greatly appreciated.

Unlike some other vendors, if you contact Mylex Technical Support with a
problem and are running Linux, they will not tell you that your use of their
products is unsupported.  Their latest product marketing literature even states
"Mylex SCSI host adapters are compatible with all major operating systems
including: ... Linux ...".

Mylex Corporation is located at 34551 Ardenwood Blvd., Fremont, California
94555, USA and can be reached at 510/796-6100 or on the World Wide Web at
http://www.mylex.com.  Mylex HBA Technical Support can be reached by electronic
mail at techsup@mylex.com, by Voice at 510/608-2400, or by FAX at 510/745-7715.
Contact information for offices in Europe and Japan is available on the Web
site.


				DRIVER FEATURES

o Configuration Reporting and Testing

  During system initialization, the driver reports extensively on the host
  adapter hardware configuration, including the synchronous transfer parameters
  requested and negotiated with each target device.  AutoSCSI settings for
  Synchronous Negotiation, Wide Negotiation, and Disconnect/Reconnect are
  reported for each target device, as well as the status of Tagged Queuing.
  If the same setting is in effect for all target devices, then a single word
  or phrase is used; otherwise, a letter is provided for each target device to
  indic