This is a subset of the documentation. To use this driver you MUST have the
full package from:

Internet:
=========

1. ftp://ftp.ccac.rwth-aachen.de/pub/jr/z8530drv-utils_3.0-3.tar.gz

2. ftp://ftp.pspt.fi/pub/ham/linux/ax25/z8530drv-utils_3.0-3.tar.gz

Please note that the information in this document may be hopelessly outdated.
A new version of the documentation, along with links to other important
Linux Kernel AX.25 documentation and programs, is available on
http://yaina.de/jreuter

-----------------------------------------------------------------------------


	 SCC.C - Linux driver for Z8530 based HDLC cards for AX.25      

   ********************************************************************

        (c) 1993,2000 by Joerg Reuter DL1BKE <jreuter@yaina.de>

        portions (c) 1993 Guido ten Dolle PE1NNZ

        for the complete copyright notice see >> Copying.Z8530DRV <<

   ******************************************************************** 


1. Initialization of the driver
===============================

To use the driver, 3 steps must be performed:

     1. if compiled as module: loading the module
     2. Setup of hardware, MODEM and KISS parameters with sccinit
     3. Attach each channel to the Linux kernel AX.25 with "ifconfig"

Unlike the versions below 2.4 this driver is a real network device
driver. If you want to run xNOS instead of our fine kernel AX.25
use a 2.x version (available from above sites) or read the
AX.25-HOWTO on how to emulate a KISS TNC on network device drivers.


1.1 Loading the module
======================

(If you're going to compile the driver as a part of the kernel image,
 skip this chapter and continue with 1.2)

Before you can use a module, you'll have to load it with

	insmod scc.o

please read 'man insmod' that comes with module-init-tools.

You should include the insmod in one of the /etc/rc.d/rc.* files,
and don't forget to insert a call of sccinit after that. It
will read your /etc/z8530drv.conf.

1.2. /etc/z8530drv.conf
=======================

To setup all parameters you must run /sbin/sccinit from one
of your rc.*-files. This has to be done BEFORE you can
"ifconfig" an interface. Sccinit reads the file /etc/z8530drv.conf
and sets the hardware, MODEM and KISS parameters. A sample file is
delivered with this package. Change it to your needs.

The file itself consists of two main sections.

1.2.1 configuration of hardware parameters
==========================================

The hardware setup section defines the following parameters for each
Z8530:

chip    1
data_a  0x300                   # data port A
c